<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Mr. Sheridan's speech after his examination before the late House of Commons on Wednesday the 15th of December, 1680</title>
            <author>Sheridan, Thomas, 1646-ca. 1688.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1681</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 25 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 3 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A59754</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S3227_VARIANT</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R37543</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">16969852</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 16969852</idno>
            <idno type="VID">105555</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A59754)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 105555)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1159:1)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Mr. Sheridan's speech after his examination before the late House of Commons on Wednesday the 15th of December, 1680</title>
                  <author>Sheridan, Thomas, 1646-ca. 1688.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>4 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London? :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1681?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Imprint suggested by Wing.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: print show-through.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sheridan, Thomas, 1646-ca. 1688.</term>
               <term>Popish Plot, 1678.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>Scott Lepisto</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>Scott Lepisto</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="speech">
            <pb facs="tcp:105555:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>M<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> 
               <hi>Sheridan</hi>'s Speech after his Examination before the late Houſe of Commons, on <hi>Wedneſday</hi> the 15<hi rend="sup">th.</hi> of <hi>December,</hi> 1680.</head>
            <p>TIs, I confeſs Sir, a great misfortune to fall under the Diſpleaſure of the Honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Houſe of Commons, it is a Burden that no man, tho' never ſo great, Is able to bear; It cannot then be a wonder, if ſo inconſiderable a Perſon, and of ſo little ſtrength as I, ſhould ſtoop under the weight; Not that I fear any Danger to my Perſon, but grieve for the wounds it gives my Reputation, which I have always valu'd above my Life, and that it might be preſerv'd ſpotleſs, I have ever made it my ſtudy to <hi>keep a good Conſcience, void of Offence, towards God and towards Man;</hi> and therefore I little expected to be brought as a Criminal to this Bar, or any Tribunal.</p>
            <p>But I am convinc'd, Innocence is no ſecurity againſt the Darts of Envy or Malice, and that he who will hazard his Body or his Soul, may take away the Life and Fame of any one at pleaſure, 'tis to men of ſuch principles I owe my preſent Trouble: I do not ſay this to reflect upon any Member of this Great and Honourable Aſſembly. My Evil is from without Doors, and I know the Authors and the Contrivance ſo well, that, if it were convenient, I cou'd name them, and trace the whole Chain, Link by Link, to the very firſt, hammer'd by Preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice, and particular Intereſt.</p>
            <p>I do not wonder that, in the preſent circumſtances, you ſhou'd have an ear open to all reports that any way relate to the publick, this is due to your Station, and to your Prudence; and becauſe Juſtice and your Honour require it, I as little doubt your reſerving the other ear for the Pleas and Defences of the Accus'd, or that you will condemn any man unheard: Upon this aſſurance it is, that I am bold to beg, with all due reſpect and reverence, that I may have liberty to ſpeak for my ſelf without interruption; If you are pleas'd to grant me this fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, I will uſe it as fully and briefly as I can, for your ſatisfaction and my own vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation.</p>
            <p>I have been repreſented (I hope without offence I may ſay, traduc'd, for ſo I can make it appear) for aſperſon of no Fortune, a Papiſt, a ſecond <hi>Coleman,</hi> and what is more ridiculous, tho' not more falſe, a Jeſuit, and the Duke's Confeſſor.</p>
            <p>In clearing my ſelf from theſe Aſperſions, I muſt be forc'd to ſay ſomething, which nothing but neceſſity, that either has none, or breaks all Laws, can excuſe from vanity. As that I was born a Gentleman, of one of the antienteſt Families, and related to many Conſiderable, in <hi>Ireland;</hi> in one County there is a Caſtle, and a large Demean, and in another a greater tract of Land for ſeveral Miles together, yet known by our Name. I need not ſay who was the head or chief, 'tis too much that my Grand-father was the laſt who enjoy'd the Eſtate, and that my Father left an Orphan in the beginning of King <hi>James</hi>'s Reign ſoon found himſelf diſpoſſeſs'd and expos'd to the World, that whole County, with five others, being intirely eſcheated to the Crown. My Parents Proteſtants, my Mother a Gentlewoman of <hi>England</hi> of good Fortune, a <hi>Foſter,</hi> who for my Fathers ſake quitted her Country and her Relations, both fam'd for honeſty, for their Loyalty and Sufferings in the <hi>late Rebellion,</hi> when my Father ſcap'd twice narrowly with his Life, and at laſt was forc'd to fly, for relieving and protecting both the Fortunes and Perſons of very many <hi>Engliſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To my Birth I had a ſuitable Education; I have ſome ſlender pretence to Letters, am not altogether a Stranger to the Civil-law, nor the Laws of <hi>England,</hi> the means intended for my Livelyhood.</p>
            <p>But, without my ſeeking or knowledge, ſome Friends procur'd for me the Collectorſhip of the Cuſtoms of <hi>Cork,</hi> and the management of moſt of the Inland-P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>enue of that Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try: This Employment, and the Accidents attending it, together with that of the <hi>Eaſt-India</hi> Prizes, and others in the laſt War with <hi>Holland,</hi> put into <hi>Kinſale,</hi> enabl'd me to bring for my own proportion of Advance-money, for the preſent Revenue-Farm of <hi>Ireland,</hi> 9532 <abbr>l.</abbr> as appears upon Record in the <hi>Chancery</hi> of <hi>England;</hi> and being by a Brother of mine, then here, without my privity or deſire, engag'd in this undertaking, and a ſtranger to all the Partnerſhip, excepting one, <hi>June</hi> laſt was 3 years I ſold my Intereſt for 4000 <abbr>l.</abbr> profit. This Money I employ'd in Corporation and Church-Leaſes, in Mortgages and other ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rities, at 10 <abbr>l.</abbr> 
               <hi>per Cent,</hi> the Intereſt of that Kingdom. And after this account, if I have no viſible real Eſtate, I hope no man can doubt but that I may live independently, tho beſides I happen to be a younger Brother, ſo far from being a prejudice, that it's poſſible to prove my advantage, being deſign'd the Heir of two elder Brothers, who neither have, nor are like to have any Children. The Bills of Exchnge drawn and remitted to and from <hi>Ireland,</hi> by Sir. <hi>John Frederick</hi> and Company, Mr. <hi>D. Arthur</hi> and other known Merchants, will ſhew my proper fond, and no man's Bounty ſupported my Expences; and therefore, becauſe I can with great Truth, I do the more freely declare, That I neither have, nor ever had any Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the Duke or Dutcheſs of <hi>York,</hi> as a Servant or Dependent, a Sallary-man or Penſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, and was ſo far from ſucceeding Mr. <hi>Coleman,</hi> that his Employment never enter'd into my Thoughts taken up with Affairs of a far different nature. My journey to <hi>Flanders</hi> was no way criminal, and in a great meaſure the effect of curioſity, having before ſeen very little of that
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:105555:2"/>Country, <hi>Holland,</hi> or <hi>Germany;</hi> and as I went not with the Duke, ſo my return in his Train was purely accident.</p>
            <p>For my Religion, as I was born of Proteſtant Parents, ſo I was all along bred a member of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and (by the Grace of God) will live and die in this Profeſſion; for it is not ſo much owing to the chance of Education, as to my choice, being ſatisfi'd by Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, by Scripture, and the Laws of my Country, no inconſiderable Argument, that of all, it is the moſt purely Chriſtian.</p>
            <p>Since I was ſeventeen years of Age I have gone duly to Church, and ſeveral times in every year receiv'd the Sacrament; I did ſo twice while in <hi>Flanders,</hi> as Dr. <hi>Lake</hi> and Dr. <hi>Doughty</hi> (the Duke's Chaplains) and others can witneſs; and I have done ſo ſix times ſince my return thence, there are in this Honourable Houſe that can teſtifie ſome part of this Truth. I have taken the Oaths of Allegiance and Supremacy eleven times, am ready to ſubmit to all further in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junctions of Law in matters of Religion, have in Diſputes encounter'd, tho' unwillingly, with many of the ſeveral Orders abroad, remain'd unſhaken in my Principles; This at <hi>Ghent,</hi> putting a Jeſuit (more zealous than the reſt) into great paſſion, made him pronounce me obſtinate, and declare, <hi>He cou'd ſooner bring over ten of the moſt rigid Phanaticks of</hi> England, <hi>than hope to make me a Proſelyte.</hi> Now if all this be not ſufficient to wipe off the imputation of Popery, I confeſs I am to ſeek for a defence.</p>
            <p>Among others 'tis objected, That by my Intereſt in his R.H. I got my Brother made a Biſhop; in oppoſition to the Lord Lieutenant of <hi>Ireland,</hi> and contrary to Merit. To this I anſwer, That my Brother has been as much, and as injuriouſly, though not ſo publicly defam'd as I; that he came off with Honour; that a peak between two Great Lords of that Kingdom, and one of the greateſt of this, did not only prevent his being ſooner promoted, but was the occaſion of his being beſpatter'd with many falſhoods and calumnies; that few in <hi>Ireland</hi> deſerve it better; that what he enjoys, he obtain'd not in oppoſition to, tho' without the recommendation of the chief Governour, nor by the mediation of the Duke, but of a great Miniſter, in the preſence of my Lord Biſhop of <hi>London,</hi> from the King's immediate Grace openly ſhewn in Council, and with a particular mark of His Royal Favour.</p>
            <p>I hope 'tis no Crime to honour and revere the Duke as he is a Prince, or if a private man to love and value his innate Worth and Qualities; or to have ſaid, as it is reported (I wiſh nothing elſe had been with leſs Truth) That I wou'd hazard my Life and Fortune to do him any lawful and juſt Service; If it be a Crime, as I can no ways apprehend of the Brother of my King, while publickly pray'd for in all the Churches of the three Kingdoms, I confeſs my ſelf guilty; But I am not ſo wedded to his Intereſt, as to eſpouſe or purſue them, if he can have any ſuch, contrary to the Duty I owe, and ever will pay my Sovereign, my Country, my Religion and my God.</p>
            <p>And I do here moſt ſolemnly proteſt, as I hope for Heaven, if I knew him in any inſtance a Conſpirator or a Traitor, I wou'd not only deteſt, but endeavour to bring him to publick Juſtice; and if ever he can be prov'd a Criminal of this nature, I will have no more reſpect nor regard, but leſs, for him, than I wou'd for any common Offender. And therefore, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the hopes of reward, or the fears of puniſhment, I declare in the preſence of the Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, If I knew any part of the <hi>Popiſh-Plot,</hi> or the perſons concern'd in't, I wou'd long ſince have reveal'd the whole Contrivance. But none in their ſenſes can believe, that a known Proteſtant cou'd be made privy to ſuch a Conſpiracy; to which, if neceſſary, might be added, that I was in a Country remote from that, where the Deſign is ſaid to be hatch'd.</p>
            <p>I own my ſelf of ſo extenſive a Charity, to love the perſons of all honeſt Men, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding their differing from me in opinion, about the Modes and Circumſtances of Religion, and to be for Liberty of Conſcience, when conſiſtent with the ſafety of the ſtate, to all quiet and peaceable Diſſenters; But when 'tis urg'd and made uſe of to other ends, or as a Cloak for Rebellion or Treachery, I abominate all ſuch Indulgence.</p>
            <p>But I will no longer dwell on this Subject, than to mind you of Collonel <hi>Manſel</hi>'s miſtake or forgetfulneſs, when he informs this Honourable Houſe, <hi>That in or about</hi> July, 1678. <hi>I din'd at his Treat for a</hi> German <hi>Lord, in order to a Deſign of his upon a Foreign Command, and that 2 or 3 days after, I ſhou'd adviſe him againſt it, telling him the Duke wou'd very ſoon have occaſion for ſuch Officers.</hi> Firſt, I do ſay, to have ſaid ſo was no Crime; But I eaſily ſee through this Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, 'tis to ſerve as an argument, that I underſtood ſomewhat of the Plot, of which I am as ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant as any man living, beyond what I have ſince learnt from the Prints and public Fame. In the next place, I do utterly deny I ever ſaid the words, becauſe I do not know the Duke had any ſuch Deſign, and am certain I cannot invent. Beſides, by many circumſtances, need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs here to mention, that Dinner was after the Courts return from <hi>Windſor,</hi> and conſequently after the breaking forth of the Plot. I deſire the Gentleman wou'd recollect himſelf; at that time he was very great and intimate with a Roman Catholick, <hi>H. N.</hi> from whom if he heard not the words, as I am not apt to imagine, I am confident he dream'd them. He cannot be ignorant that I knew why he was disbanded in <hi>Ireland,</hi> &amp;c. and that I always declin'd, not only as having no Intereſt, but as unwilling for other reaſons, to introduce him to the Duke, as he often preſſ'd; and therefore he made his application to others, but with us ill ſucceſs.</p>
            <p>And now give me leave, I beſeech you, Mr. <hi>Speaker,</hi> to anſwer an Objection, that I
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:105555:2"/>have preſcrib'd a way how the King ſhou'd live without Parliaments: I am ſo far from enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining ſuch a thought, that I ever eſteem'd the Conſtitutions of <hi>England</hi> by King, Lords and Commons the happieſt kind of Government in the world; and if the diſcourſe called, <hi>The Riſe and Power of Parliaments,</hi> &amp;c. be mine, of which many will have me the Author, the reading it, wou'd be of this a ſufficient Confutation: In that, Parliaments are magnifi'd, their power rather enlarg'd than leſſen'd, and their frequent meetings recommended as moſt convenient.</p>
            <p>In a word, whatever Character my Adverſaries have given of me, I am not a Proteſtant in Maſquerade. I can neither Lie nor Diſſemble, I am really what I profeſs, and as the word is commonly taken, no lover of Arbitrary Government, in any ſingle or complicated body.</p>
            <p>As to the Letter Subſcrib'd by <hi>Fitz-James,</hi> I do ſincerely proteſt I have no Acquaintance with any of the Name, nor ever ſaw the Hand before, nor the intended Meſſenger <hi>C.</hi> who not finding me, left it with the Maid-ſervant: But in this there is nothing Criminal.</p>
            <p>As to the Computations, they are a Tranſcript from a Paper of Sir <hi>Peter Petts,</hi> containing the number of Conformiſts, Non-Conformiſts and Papiſts throughout <hi>England,</hi> taken by the Biſhops order, in, or about the time of the General Indulgence, and by him produc'd preſently after the <hi>Plot,</hi> upon the talk that there were fifty thouſand Papiſts, able to bear Arms, within <hi>Temple-Bar</hi> and about <hi>Weſtminſter;</hi> a number near double to what, at the taking this ſurvey, they were found men, women and children in the whole Kingdom.</p>
            <p>For the Copy of my Couſin <hi>Wilſons</hi> Writing, I confeſs it the only thing I endeavour'd to evade, having ingenuouſly, and without reſerve anſwer'd all other queſtions. That individual Paper I never ſaw before the preceding night, when meeting it in the Drawer of my Bed-Chamber, (always open, whether I am at home or abroad) I laid it uppermoſt with purpoſe of Inquiring how he came by it, and whether he knew the Author; But not ſeeing him till next day in preſence of the Members ſent to ſearch my Lodgings, I cou'd not ask him, and was ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priz'd to have ſo Indiſcreet and Reflective a Paper found in his hand, and among mine. 'Tis true, that about three Weeks before, I found another of the ſame Contents, in an Old Crabbed hand, to me unknown; which after I had Read, and concluded it might poſſibly be left by ſome of my Acquaintance in their Viſits, and being unable to gueſs at the perſon, not knowing how long it had layn there, being Dated above a Month before, I immediatly threw it into the fire. Yet in this Paper, which has made ſo great a noiſe, there is neither Felony nor Treaſon; and being the Act of another, and never by me publiſh'd, having neither Sub, nor Superſcription, nor Writ to, nor for from me, nor Copi'd by my Order, cannot, I preſume, be a Libel, nor I hope imputed to me, to whom it came perfectly by Accident: If it were lawful to ſpeak ones gueſſes from the Contents, it ſhou'd ſeem to have come from a Learned Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, one of your own Members, then in the Country, Skill'd in the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Tongue, to which both my Couſin and I are perfect ſtrangers; nor was either of us out of <hi>London</hi> then, or for ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time before. If I cou'd as well hit upon the perſon, as his Quality, I wou'd give a more Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfactory account of this matter; and I hope this Honourable Aſſembly will the ſooner Credit me, when they reflect, that upon ſeeing another Paper of my Kinſmans writing, I wou'd not by a lie deny this to be his hand.</p>
            <p>As for my Writing to Mr. <hi>Gadbury,</hi> I refer my ſelf to the Letter in Sir <hi>W. Waller</hi>'s hands: I have told you the accidental occaſion; I deſir'd from him, (whoſe Acquaintance I knew large, even among the Members of that Parliament) the moſt material of public News; I neither ask'd for Schemes or Figures, I have ever Laugh'd at the idle and ridiculous Art of Judicial Aſtrology, invented, at leaſt practis'd, to Impoſe upon, and Pick the Pockets of the Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant and the Credulous.</p>
            <p>And now as to the Cauſe of my Commitment: The ſtory Dr. <hi>D.</hi> told me as News, of <hi>Peter Norris</hi> his knowing as much of the <hi>Plot</hi> as any man in <hi>England,</hi> his going, or being gone into <hi>France</hi> to fetch a Prieſt to be a Witneſs. I can only ſay, as near as I remember, I gave the ſame account to Mr. <hi>Secretary;</hi> not as an Informer, but as News; for not being look'd upon as ſuch, I was not deſir'd to Swear, nor cou'd I to a hear-ſay: In this I call Heaven to witneſs I had no Siniſter deſign, but an Honeſt intention of having the full Truth brought to Light: Nor do I know, nor have I any reaſon to believe, that Mr. <hi>Secretary</hi>'s after proceedings were from any other principle. Upon my telling him the Name of <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris,</hi> and his ſaying he had never before heard it, and commanding me to ſend the Doctor to him, or the others Deſcription; As ſoon as I met with the Doctor, which was ſeveral dayes after this Diſcourſe; and he as not knowing Mr. <hi>Secretary</hi> refuſing to go, I deſir'd from him the Deſcription, which ſome time after he brought me; I gave or ſent to Mr. <hi>Secretary,</hi> for I cannot tell whether. But of this I am certain, that all I knew of the Affair, was from the Doctor only; and that I never communicated it to any, but Mr. <hi>Secretary,</hi> and that by what I writ under the Deſcription, appears to be near a Month after <hi>Norris</hi> his departure, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently cou'd not be deſign'd to ſtop his Journey, or prevent the Prieſts coming over, or obſtruct the fuller diſcovery of the Plot, which no man living deſires more than my ſelf, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving it the Intereſt of every honeſt Subject and Proteſtant, (out of which number I cannot be excluded) to have all in't, from the higheſt to the loweſt puniſh'd according to merit, and that tranquility it has ſo long diſturb'd, re-ſettl'd in the Kingdom: And now I hope none
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:105555:3"/>of the Members of this Honourable Houſe can imagine I cou'd be guilty of ſo Horrid a Crime, as having any knowledge of the Prieſts being poiſon'd, as is ſuſpected, or given out he might be. I am ſo ignorant of this, or any part of the Conſpiracy, that I do not ſo much deſpiſe, as decline, becauſe not needing it, the generous offer of Mr. <hi>Speaker,</hi> or other Members Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion for my Pardon: I acknowledge, as I ought, the Favour with all fitting reſpect; but I thank God, I am ſo Innocent, that I dare, as now I do, challenge the whole world, to make out one particular, where in Word or Action, in the whole courſe of my life, I have done or ſpoken falſly, or unjuſtly; and yet no man ever ſuffer'd more Calumnies, without any cauſe, or the leaſt ſhadow of Truth, beyond the witty malice of thoſe, whoſe Eyes are blinded, and Conſciences ſear'd by Envy and Intereſt, who from pretended Friends are become my real Adverſaries, contrary to Reaſon and Juſtice. But further, none can believe I cou'd keep any dangerous Correſpondence, when its well known that for theſe three years and a half all my Letters were no otherwiſe Directed, than for me at the <hi>Royal Coffee-houſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Beſides it appear'd at the Committee by <hi>Norris</hi> his own Papers, that this Prieſt <hi>Dowdall,</hi> (whoſe Name I never heard before) died <hi>September</hi> laſt was twelve Months, eight Months be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I heard there was ſuch a man in the world as <hi>Norris,</hi> and at a time when I was in another Country. And ſince you have thought fit to acquit Dr. <hi>D.</hi> who was my Author and Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal, and who own'd himſelf a <hi>Roman Catholick;</hi> I hope you will not think it equal, that I a known ſincere Proteſtant, and but an Acceſſary, ſhou'd ſtand Committed, and Committed after ſuch a manner, as neither Felon nor Traitor, not only Accus'd, but Convicted, cou'd ſuffer a Cloſer Confinement.</p>
            <p>And here, Mr. <hi>Speaker,</hi> I intreat your leave to ask Pardon, if at the Committee my behavi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our has offended any of the Members of this Honourable Houſe, and to ſay, whatever heat I expreſs'd, was the effect of Paſſion, to which I was mov'd, by hearing ſeveral of them in public, as at <hi>Locketts</hi> and other Eating and <hi>Coffee-houſes,</hi> had call'd me <hi>Papiſt,</hi> and a ſecond <hi>Coleman,</hi> with other Aſperſions I cou<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>d not bear without reſentment: To this was added my being commanded a Meſſenger for Dr. <hi>D.</hi> an office beneath me, and wherein I cou'd not expect to be ſucceſsful, not knowing whether he wou'd appear without Compulſion. I hope it will not be accounted an unexpiable Crime for a Gentleman of more Years and Diſcretion, than I can pretend to, to ſhew himſelf diſturb'd at a conoeiv'd Indignity or Affront; and in hopes it may not be accounted ſo hainous, I do once more withall due Submiſſion beg pardon. There is one thing more I cannot without trouble touch upon, the Reflections the Written Votes, very different from the Printed, bring upon my Reputation: In thoſe 'tis ſaid, it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears that I have ſucceeded Mr. <hi>Coleman,</hi> than which there never was a more groundleſs, falſe, or malicious invention: And alſo that I queſtion'd your Authority, and ſaid your Proceedings look'd like the late Rebellion. However Sir <hi>William Roberts</hi> came to make the Report, my words were to Sir <hi>John Morton</hi> in another Room, and to him I appeal whether they were not thus. Upon his adviſing than I ſhou'd fare the better, if I freely ſhew'd my Papers, I told him I wou'd not hid one, nor diſpute their power, tho I had heard others did; and that the Seizing Cloſets and Writings, was not only Illegal, but look'd upon as one of the Cauſes of the laſt Rebellion; thereupon he wiſh'd I had not ſaid the Words: I reply'd, I meant no harm by thoſe Objections, and notwithſtanding my mentioning them, they ſhou'd find in me a readineſs to obey, and an intire ſubmiſſion; and added if the were offenſive, I unſaid them, and ask'd his pardon, as I now humbly do from the whole Houſe, if I am thought herein to have offended. And to do Sir <hi>John</hi> Juſtice, he was pleas'd to promiſe he wou'd take no notice of the Diſcourſe, unleſs commanded; to whom with the reſt of the Committee I refer my ſelf, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of my own accord I was not going along with them, when I met your Meſſenger.</p>
            <p>If I had been guilty of any Crime, I had not only Warning, but Threats and Advices to fly many days, ſome weeks before, when I was told by Letters from unknown hands, and by ſeveral perſons of Honour and Quality, that I was deſign'd to be brought into trouble; I need not in this place ſay, for what reaſon. And here I cannot by the way but take notice of a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port made by Juſtice <hi>Waroup</hi> at this Bar, and ſo read at <hi>Coffee-houſes;</hi> that he ſhou'd have Search'd Mr. <hi>Sheridans</hi> Lodgings, and there found only a Parcel of <hi>Popiſh</hi> Books, whereas he never was in mine, but at Mr. <hi>Brunetly</hi>'s Houſe, an <hi>Italian</hi> Merchant, whoſe Books thoſe muſt have been and therefore I hope this was ſome Clarks, rather than his miſtake.</p>
            <p>And now ſince no man can be plac'd beyond the reach of Malice, and the devices of the wicked; and that I happen to be brought hither as a ſuppos'd Criminal, I am extreamly pleas'd, I have the good fortune to meet with ſo wiſe and equal Judges as compoſe this Auguſt and Honourable Aſſembly; where I am ſo far from fears that I do not doubt, but upon an exact <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, and an Impartial Examination my having been ſo infinitely produc'd, and ſo wrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully expos'd to the publick; will be ſo far from gratifying my Adverſaries unjuſt deſires, that they will not only be defeated, but my ſelf greatly advantag <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> and therefore I leave my Cauſe as the Footſtool of your Juſtice, and willingly ſubmit to your Pleaſure and Determina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion  praying no other favour, than what I am <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> you wou'd grant without asking, your full Conſideration of the whole Matter, your ſpeedy Condemnation or Acquittal, as I ſhall be found Guilty or Innocent.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
